Hi everyone.
I'm Karishma. I'm a sports scientist.
And as a sports scientist, I get invited
to a lot of parties so people can ask me
this question.
And I get asked this a lot. And I just
wanted to go through this with you
because this is kind of the essence of
what we do as sports scientists.
Um
Well, if someone would ask me this
question
a lot of parents come to me with kids
and they're like, "My kid is 7 years
old. I need them to become a pro
athlete. You have the school title. Tell
me how to do it."
My answer to them at a party would be
exactly this.
Well, we have this idea that if we want
to specialize in a certain sport, which
is we start as soon as we give birth to
the child, we put them into that sport,
we allow them to kind of
keep practicing, keep practicing so they
get good at it. But science tells us
otherwise. What science is actually
telling us that that is going to cause a
larger problem later on because what's
going to happen apart from the child
getting really bored of playing the
sport its entire life
you will have an increased probability
of burnout.
Athletes will quit when they're older.
More typically, when they start really
young, they tend to leave the sport at
an an earlier age.
Um there's an the overuse injury, right?
So if I start cricket um when I'm
five and I've been playing cricket my
entire life, by the time I reach 30, the
same movements that I'm using to play
the sport will be overused. So that body
part of mine is wearing out.
Children need to develop first as
athletes. They need to develop a
physical ability first.
And then they're able to specialize in
sport.
So look, sports ultimately is something
that human beings have created and
defined. Okay, if I do this movement,
then it's called cricket. And if I do
this movement, then it's called
football. And if I do this movement,
it's called um you know, rugby. But
ultimately, the human body doesn't
really know all these rules. It just
needs to develop and be really fit and
work well as a machine before we can
play a sport.
You can develop the same cardiovascular
ability via
um to play tennis via playing football.
It's the same thing for the body.
Similarly with golf and cricket. And in
fact, now sports science is finding that
it's actually essential to play multiple
sports if you want to excel in any one.
Um AB de Villiers, one of the best
batsman in the world, one of the fittest
batsman in the world, actually is a
really really good athlete. And that is
why he's such a good batsman. He's known
to have played a lot of rugby,
badminton, participated in swimming,
track and field, and tennis. In fact,
you'd be surprised to know that most
Olympic athletes don't specialize before
the age of 15. So, when someone asked me
that question about their 7-year-old,
I'll be like, just first let them play.
Let them play everything. Next, I get
questions such as, how do I improve my
tennis serve? And this is what we as
sports scientists do. We take the
science, we go to something like the
kinetic chain theory, which says that
the body exists as a series of chains.
So, the movement at one joint will
eventually affect the movement at
another joint. So, when you move from
your ankle,
it gets translated to the knee, the
movement at the knee affects the
movement at the hip, and like that. So,
to get a really good tennis serve,
the ideal the maximum amount of power
you can generate is 4,000 watts of
power. So, that is the same amount of
energy that you would require to climb
up 12 flights of stairs in 2 seconds.
That's the kind of power we're talking.
Now, you cannot develop that just from
your shoulder and a flick of the wrist.
There's obviously more to that story,
and in that gray area is where science
comes in.
How we would explain this to an athlete
is that
most of your force is generated from the
ground and then in fact 50% if you look
at that graph is generated from the
ground and that force from the ground is
translated into your body through all of
your joints and eventually into the
swing.
So when I'm advising on technique, this
is kind of how you would apply sports
science to improve our technique in say
a tennis serve.
This is another key question which is a
constant debate, which is the best body
type for health and sports. Well, the
answer like everything else in sports
science is that well, it depends.
This person here is a sprinter and this
body type is that for a marathon runner.
So a body type will develop based on
what it has to do, based on the purpose.
Marathon runners need to have they need
to be lighter, they need to run for
longer, they're burning fats for energy.
Whereas a sprinter who's only running
maybe a few seconds is using immediate
energy which is stored in the muscles.
So that's why they have huge muscles so
they can store all that energy and use
it when they need. Now
a sprinter is probably going to be a
worse marathon runner than me because
I'm somewhere in the middle. I'm a
normal human being and I can kind of
work both my systems. But when you're
talking about sports, you're not talking
about normal health, you're talking
about the extremes in one way or
another. Whose Athletes are people whose
body types have specialized to an
extreme in one direction.
For example, if you look at water polo,
the all water polo players generally it
would be advantageous to them to have a
really long forearm to arm ratio so they
can throw the ball further.
I mean NBA, one in 10 men are 7 ft tall
whereas the average male height is 5'10
in the rest of the population. The
average height of the elite female
gymnast, to be a gymnast you want to be
tiny, you want to to able to roll in the
air, you want to be able to spin. So,
those body types come to an advantage
when you are
specializing in a particular sport. In
fact, my favorite example is that of
Phelps, who's just apparently touted as
a genetic freak of nature, somebody
who's created for to swim. He just
happens to have every genetic advantage
that helps him in the water.
For example, most people have a wingspan
that is the same as their height.
That's kind of how we are. But, Phelps,
who's 6'4", has a wingspan of 6'7". That
allows him to move his arms further in
water and gives him a competition over
the next person. And I mean,
advantage over the next person.
Similarly, his shoe size is much bigger
than the average shoe shoe size,
allowing him to have natural flippers.
His chest is double-jointed, which
allows him to get more flexibility in
the water and to move faster.
I mean, there are multiple This is only
a list of some that he has. He just
naturally produces less lactate, gets
less tired.
So, I'm just telling you this is sort of
an example of the kind of things that we
look at in sports science.
And he has won 28 gold medals. He's
probably the most celebrated, most
successful swimmers of all time at the
Olympic level.
So, it
encourages us or it makes it easier for
us to feel that, "Look, there's a
formula. He has these things. So, should
we look for
people with long arms? Or should we look
for people with bigger legs? Is that
going to translate into Olympic gold
medals?" And that's kind of where sports
science was when I studied it, that the
human body
it is basically just a blend of
biology, psychology, nutritional
science, biochemistry, multiple fields.
But, ultimately, we're looking to see
how can we create a better human.
And that's why the way I view it and
interpret it is we're working at the
edge of human ability. You know, if Bolt
is running at 9.7 in a sprint, how do we
get him to 9.6? How do we work at that
edge and how do we make it better? And
what are the rules? And that gives us
two gives us a lot of insight into how
the human body works and how it
functions. Generally,
sport science is in summary this slide.
We We view the body as a sum of its
parts. Okay, what's happening at the DNA
level? Are we, you know, the genetic
code is coding for proteins, enzymes,
and that is translating into certain um
physiological, you know, outcome of the
body, and that helps them in exercise.
We look at heart rate. We look at
systems of the body, how they interact.
And it's it's actually really cool as a
subject. But,
now I'm more than a sport scientist in
terms that I just view myself as a
scientist and someone who's very
interested in the human body and how it
works. Sport science is one way to view
it, and generally we view it as, like I
showed you, the sum of its parts. This
is what's happening. This is the
formula. This is how the human body
works. Let's just add it up. And if you
put this input, you're going to get
another output.
In the '80s,
um scientists tried to recreate breast
milk. They took um the breast milk. They
created a formula, and they said that,
"Look, if a child is unable to be
breastfed by the mother, let us create
something where we can just give." So,
they took the milk, they measured it in
the lab, made an, you know, a scientific
version of it, and started selling this
formula.
Years later, scientists have realized
that the kids who were on the formula
started getting more ill than the kids
who were on breast milk. And then they
reopened that chapter, looked into it,
and now they found something really
interesting. They have discovered that
it is not
just what's in the milk. It is the
communication between the mother and
child during breastfeeding, such that if
the child is lacking in a particular
nutrient, if the child is picking up a
particular illness, the mother's body
reacts to that and creates certain
proteins that the child needs, creates
the enzymes, and gives it to the child
through the breast milk. I mean, that's
a beautiful thought. You can't formula
that. No, you cannot recreate that and
that is kind of what I'm starting to see
more and more of these kind of trends in
the human body.
Cardiovascular disease, one of the
biggest killers. People are saying, "Oh,
it's lack of exercise. It's, you know,
eating wrong. It's cholesterol, this,
that." I've read a study recently that
says that owning a pet, owning a dog can
reduce your risk of cardiovascular
disease.
And literally by just petting a dog for
a few days a week, people have lowered
their blood pressure, lowered their
heart rate. They've even reduced
cholesterol levels.
I mean, that's a great excuse for kids
who want to pick up a pet and their
parents are saying, "No." You can just
have them check the science on that.
And
here's another one that I love because I
did neuroscience before I did sports
science. So, earlier it was believed
that the brain forms from the age of 0
to 18 and then it's just formed and then
your brain is now who you are and
everything you do is now set in stone.
And that's why we attributed everything
to our personality and, you know,
whatever you This is your nature and
it's your personality. This These are
your preferences.
Well, there's a concept called
neuroplasticity,
which now looks at the brain as
something that re-wires itself every
single day. Every part of your brain is
changing every single day and it's
changing based on what you eat, what
exercise you do, who you talk to. After
this TED Talk, your brain is going to go
back and re-wire itself. That is how
quickly your brain is changing.
So, there's no formula for that. You
cannot formula it. There are multiple,
multiple, multiple experiences and
inputs that we are having and reacting
to on a daily basis. Even if you take a
science that seems as sure of itself as
genetics, which is we have a lot of
people in science who think that, "Oh,
it's all in the genes and everything's
written and it's all predetermined."
Which is kind of true. The genetics is
the script of what your cells will do,
how they will express themselves.
Genetics is ultimately your you know,
it's like the it's it's literally the
script of your life.
But,
now here's an interesting science that's
come up called epigenetics, which looks
at
which genes are turned on and off based
on your experiences. So, I might have
the genes for certain things. I might
have the genes for obesity. I might have
the genes for
you know, certain diseases. I might have
the genes for whatever I may I may need
the genes for, but whether they be
turned on or off is based on my
experiences. It's based on my choices
that I make. It's based on the input I
make. We have We will never be able to
formulate that. So, the code is there.
Well, we are more like directors in our
lives for the script. The script is
written, but the way we direct it, our
input, our interactions, our experiences
have a much larger impact than we
previously thought. And this is science
saying this. This is not something
mystical. This is not some you know, tap
into your magic kind of thing. This is
pure science.
So, instead of viewing the body as just
like a pure machine that you can kind of
some of its parts tweak. You give this
input and we get a certain output.
I feel that
we have programs that we have understood
this. We've understood it quite well.
But, and I view that as something that
we have which is the best medicine in
the world. We have fantastic knowledge
about the body. We have the science. We
understand different systems so well.
There is volumes of information out
there and so much research going on in
the body. But, you can have the best
medicine in the world. Assuming this
pill has the best medicine in the world
for say, I don't know, cancer.
I can guarantee you that if you take
this medicine, you will cure cancer or
you can cure diabetes or you can cure
whatever.
But, if the capsule that that medicine
is delivered in is not something that is
received by the human being, if the
[snorts] human body is unable to digest
that medicine, it is completely useless.
So, my parallel is this. I've been
working in science for a long time.
[snorts]
I've studied it.
And I find that we are we have such
fantastic brilliant knowledge, but we're
not delivering it to people so they are
able to make sense of it. We're not
delivering it in context. We're not
delivering it to human beings. We're
just creating this amazing knowledge
which gets created in universities and
it gets created, you know, through
research. It goes through so much time
before it actually reaches people and
changes their lives. That lag between
creating, researching something, getting
it published, teaching it in a
university, a student going to study it,
coming back home and applying it could
be